<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  ~ Copyright 2010 Andreas Veithen
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <title>Chainsaw for WAS Manual</title>
        <releaseinfo>&version;</releaseinfo>
        <legalnotice>
            <para>
                Copyright 2010 Andreas Veithen
            </para>
            <para>
                Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
                you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
                You may obtain a copy of the License at
            </para>
            <para>
                <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"/>
            </para>
            <para>
                Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
                distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
                WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
                See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
                limitations under the License.
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Getting started</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>
                The aim of the Chainsaw4WAS is to integrate Apache Chainsaw with
                WebSphere Application Server.
                <ulink url="http://logging.apache.org/chainsaw/">Apache Chainsaw</ulink>
                is a GUI-based log viewer based on the popular log4j framework. It ships
                with a number of plugins that can be used to receive log events from
                remote processes. However, for this to work, these processes must use
                log4j and must be configured with the corresponding log4j appenders.
            </para>
            <para>
                On the other hand, WebSphere has a centralized logging subsystem that
                is exposed at the JMX level as an MBean called
                <classname>RasLoggingService</classname>. It processes log events
                from other WebSphere components as well as from the deployed applications,
                provided that these applications use one of the Jakarta Commons Logging (JCL) or
                java.util.logging (JUL) APIs. This is also the component that
                manages the well known <filename>SystemOut.log</filename> file.
                <classname>RasLoggingService</classname> supports JMX notifications, so that
                it is possible to connect to a remote WAS instance and receive log events
                from this server in realtime. The aim of the Chainsaw4WAS project is to
                allow these log events to be visualized in Apache Chainsaw.
            </para>
            <para>
                The heard of the Chainsaw4WAS project is a custom log4j plugin
                (more precisely an implementation of the <classname>org.apache.log4j.plugins.Receiver</classname>
                interface) that connects to a local or remote <classname>RasLoggingService</classname> and
                that injects the received log events into the log4j framework.
                As discussed in the following sections, the solution can be deployed
                in different ways, but the end-result always looks as shown in
                <xref linkend="chainsaw4was-screenshot"/>.
            </para>
            <figure id="chainsaw4was-screenshot">
                <title>Log events from a WAS instance displayed in Chainsaw</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="chainsaw4was-screenshot.png" format="PNG" scale="60" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>
                Please note that this project is currently based on Chainsaw version 2.0alpha-1,
                which is the last available release and has been built with log4j 1.3alpha-7.
                The 1.3 branch has been discontinued<footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/"/>.</para></footnote>,
                but many features originally developed for log4j 1.3 have been back-ported to log4j 1.2.
                At the time of writing, work is in progress on Chainsaw 2.1, which will be based on
                log4j 1.2.x. Chainsaw4WAS will be ported to that version of Chainsaw as soon as
                an official release is available.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Deployment options</title>
            <para>
                Chainsaw4WAS can be used with two deployment variants:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Using the ZeroConf EAR. This requires deploying a special EAR file on each of the
                        WAS instances to be monitored using Chainsaw. The code in this EAR file registers
                        a notification listener on the local <classname>RasLoggingService</classname> and
                        exposes the log events using a protocol supported out-of-the-box by Chainsaw.
                        The component advertises itself using ZeroConf, so that it will be discovered
                        automatically by Chainsaw. However, this only works if the workstation running
                        Chainsaw is in the same network as the server.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The advantage of this deployment option is its simplicity and the fact that
                        it works with the standard Chainsaw distribution. However, it is only suitable
                        for test and development environments, but not for production environments,
                        especially not for large scale WebSphere ND installations.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Using the RAS logging receiver plugin in Chainsaw. When this option is used,
                        no particular setup is necessary on the WAS instances, and Chainsaw connects
                        remotely to one or more <classname>RasLoggingService</classname> instances
                        using one of the supported JMX connectors.
                        This deployment option requires a specially built Chainsaw distribution because the plugin
                        depends on libraries from the WebSphere runtime. For legal reasons,
                        these libraries cannot be redistributed, and the custom Chainsaw4WAS distribution
                        is therefore not available for download. Instead, it must be built from source code,
                        which requires a local WebSphere 7.0 installation.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This option should be preferred for production environments. It is also more suitable
                        for WAS ND installations, because only a connection to the deployment manager is
                        required, but not to the individual application servers. Finally, this option
                        should always be used in environments where ZeroConf
                        doesn't work, i.e. if the application servers are located in a different network than the
                        workstations running Chainsaw.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
